I dabble in design. I'm a curator of architecture and design;
أنا أعمل بالتصميم، وأنا أمينة بمعارض للتصميم و الفن المعماري
I happen to be at the Museum of Modern Art.
في متحف للفن الحديث
But what we're going to talk about today
لكن المهم هو ما سنتكلم عنه اليوم
is really design. Really good designers are like sponges:
هو التصميم. المصممون الجيدون مثل الاسفنج.
they really are curious
عندهم فضول للمعرفة.
and absorb every kind of information that comes their way,
يستوعبون كل انواع العلومات التى تأتي في طريقهم.
and transform it so that it can be used by people like us.
و يحولوها كي يستخدمها الناس مثلنا
And so that gives me an opportunity,
و هذا يتيح لي الفرصة
because every design show that I curate
لأن كل عرض تصميمات أكون أمينته
kind of looks at a different world. And it's great,
و كأنه آت من عالم مختلف
because it seems like every time I change jobs.
لأنه يبدو مثل كل مرة أقوم فيها تغيير عملي
And what I'm going to do today is I'm going to give you a preview
و ما سأقوم بعمله اليوم هو أن أعرض لكم فكرة عامة
of the next exhibition that I'm working on, which is called
عن المعرض القادم الذي أعمل عليه، و أسمه
"Design and the Elastic Mind."
"التصميم و العقل المطاط"
The world that I decided to focus on this particular time
العالم الذي قررت أن أركز عليه في هذه المرة تحديدا
is the world of science and the world of technology.
هو عالم العلوم والتكنولوجا
Technology always comes into play when design is involved,
التكنولوجية تظهر على الساحة عندما يشارك التصميم
but science does a little less.
لكن العلم يفعل القليل
But designers are great at taking big revolutions that happen
لكن المصممون عظماء في إحداث الطفرات التي تحدث
and transforming them so that we can use them.
و تحويرها لكي نستطيع استخدامها
And this is what this exhibition looks at.
وهذا ما ينظر اليه هذا المعرض.
If you think about your life today,
إذا فكرت في حياتك الآن
you go every day through many different scales,
فأنت تمر في كل يوم خلال عدة مستويات
many different changes of rhythm and pace.
عدة تغيرات في الإيقاع و الوتيرة
You work over different time zones, you talk to very different people,
ربما تعمل في أوقات ومناطق زمنية مختلفه، تتكلم مع أشخاص مختلفين
you multitask. We all know it, and we do it kind of automatically.
تتعامل مع عدة مهام في نفس الوقت. كلنا نعرف ذلك و نتعامل معه بنوع من التلقائيه
Some of the minds in this audience are super elastic,
بعض عقول المستمعين مرنه جدا
others are a little slower,
البعض الآخر أقل مرونه و أبطأ قليلا
others have a few stretch marks, but nonetheless
وآخرون لديهم بعض علامات الانتشار و تأثير الإتساع، ولكن مع ذلك
this is a quite exceptional audience from that viewpoint.
فالمستمعون الى حد ما استثناء في هذه النقطة
Other people are not as elastic.
فبعض الناس ليسو بنفس المرونه
I can't get my father in Italy to work on the Internet.
أنا لا أستطيع أن أجعل أبي في إيطاليا أن يعمل على الإنترنت
He doesn't want to put high-speed Internet at home.
فهو لا يريد أن يدخل الإنترنت السريع إلى المنزل
And that's because there's some little bit of fear,
و هذا بسبب وجود بعض المخاوف البسيطه
little bit of resistance or just clogged mechanisms.
بعض المقاومة و ربما هي فقط عوائق في الإنفتاح على الجديد.
So designers work on this particular malaise that we have,
لذا المصممون يعملون على مثل هذه العوائق والعقبات لدينا
these kinds of discomforts that we have,
مثل هذه المضايقات لدينا.
and try to make life easier for us.
ومحاولة لجعل الحياة أسهل لنا
Elasticity of mind is something that we really need, you know,
مرونة العقل شئ فعلا نريده، كما تعلمون
we really need, we really cherish and we really work on.
نحتاج أن نحافظ عليه و نتطوره.
And this exhibition is about the work of designers
و هذا المعرض من أجل أعمال المصممين
that help us be more elastic,
التي تساعدنا كي نكون أكثر مرونه
and also of designers that really work on this elasticity
وأيضا المصممين الذين يعملون فعلا على هذه المرونه
as an opportunity. And one last thing is that
كفرصه. و هناك شئ آخر و هو
it's not only designers, but it's also scientists.
ليس فقط المصصممين و لكن أيضا العلماء.
And before I launch into the display of some of the slides
وقبل أن أبدأ في العرض التفصيلي
and into the preview, I would like to point out
على الشاشة، أود أن أشير الى
this beautiful detail about scientists and design.
هذه التفصيلة الجميلة عن العلم و التصميم
You can say that the relationship between science and design
تستطيع القول بأن العلاقة بين العلم والتصميم
goes back centuries. You can of course talk about
بدأت منذ عدة قرون. فبالطبع تستطيع التحدث عن
Leonardo da Vinci and many other Renaissance men and women --
"ليوناردو دا فينشي" و العديد من الرجال والنساء من عصر النهضة
and there's a gigantic history behind it.
و التاريخ العريق وراء ذلك
But according to a really great science historian you might know,
و لكن وفقا لمؤرخ العلم العظيم الذي ربما تعرفونه،
Peter Galison -- he teaches at Harvard --
" بيتر جاليسون" المدرس في هارفرد
what nanotechnology in particular and quantum physics
ما جلبته النانوتكنولوجي تحديدا و فيزياء الكم
have brought to designers is this renewed interest,
للمصممين فقد جددت الإهتمام
this real passion for design.
و شغف التصميم
So basically, the idea of being able to build things bottom up,
لذلك، ففكرة المقدرة على بناء الأشياء من الأدنى نحو لأعلى
atom by atom, has made them all into tinkerers.
و حجر بعد حجر، قد جعل منهم مفكرين.
And all of a sudden scientists are seeking designers,
و فجأه أصبح العلماء يسعون إلى المصممين
just like designers are seeking scientists.
تماما كما يسعى المصممون إلى العلماء
It's a brand-new love affair that we're trying to cultivate
إنها علاقة حب جديدة التي نحاول أن نرعاها
at MOMA. Together with Adam Bly, who is the founder of Seed magazine --
في "موما" مع "أدم بلاي" مؤسس مجلة "سيد"
that's now a multimedia company, you might know it --
و هي الآن شركة "ملتي ميديا" التي ربما تعرفونها
we founded about a year ago a monthly salon
أسسنا منذ سنة ندوة شهرية بين
for designers and scientists, and it's quite beautiful.
المصممين و العلماء، انه شئ رائع
And Keith has come, and also Jonathan has come and many others.
و "كيث" شاركت، أيضا "جوناثان" و كذلك العديد من الناس.
And it was great, because at the beginning was this apology fest --
و كان ذلك رائعا، لأنه في البداية كان هناك "مهرجان الإعتذار"
you know, scientists would tell designers,
فالعلماء كانوا يقولون للمصممين،
you know, I don't know what style is, I'm not really elegant.
لست متأكدا من الطراز و الستايل، أنا لا أفهم في الأناقة
And designers would like, oh, I don't know how to do an equation,
و المصممون ربما يقولون، لست أعرف كيف أحل المعادلات
I don't understand what you're saying. And then all of a sudden
ولست أفهم ماذا تقصد من هذا الكلام. وبدون مقدمات
they really started talking each others' language,
بدؤا يتحدثون بلغة بعضهم الآخر
and now we're already at the point that they collaborate.
و نحن الآن فعلا في المرحلة أنهم بدؤا التعاون
Paul Steinhardt, a physicist from New York,
مثلا "بول ستاينهارت" وهو عالم من نيويورك،
and Aranda/Lasch, architects, collaborated in an installation
و "أرندا/لاش" وهي معمارية، تعاونا في إنشاء
in London at the Serpentine.
في "سيربنتاين" في لندن
And it's really interesting to see how this happens.
و قد كان ممتعا رؤية ذلك يحدث
The exhibition will talk about the work
المعرض سيتحدث عن العمل
of both designers and scientists,
الذي شارك فيه مصمم وعالم
and show how they're presenting the possibilities of the future to us.
و نرى كيف سيعرضون لنا إمكانات المستقبل
I'm showing to you
و كما ترون فأنا أعرض لكم
different sections of the show right now,
عدة مقاطع من العرض الآن،
just to give you a taste of it.
فقط لأعطيكم فكرة عن مذاقها
Nanophysics and nanotechnology, for instance,
لكن "النانوفيزيا" و "النانوتكنولوجي" على سبيل المثال
have really opened the designer's mind.
قد وسعت أفق المصممين.
In this case I'm showing more the designers' work,
و أنا الآن أعرض أعمال للمصممين أكثر في هذه الحالة
because they're the ones that have really been stimulated.
لأنهم كانو الأكثر تجاوبا وتأثرا
A lot of the objects in the show are concepts,
الكثير من العناصر في العرض مازالت مجرد أفكار
not objects that exist already. But what you're looking at here
فهي ليست عناصر موجوده بالفعل. لكن ما ترونه الآن
is the work of some scientists from UCLA.
هو من أعمال بعض العلماء من "UCLA"
This kind of alphabet soup is a new way to mark proteins --
هذا النوع من الحساء الأبجدي هي طريقة جديدة لتحديد البروتين
not only by color but literally by alphabet letters.
ليس فقط بالألوان و لكن أيضا بالحروف
So they construct it, and they can construct all kinds of forms
وبالتالي تم بناؤه وباستطاعتهم بناء جميع الأشكال
at the nanoscale. This is the work of design students
على مستوى النانو. وهذا ما يقوم طلاب التصميم
from the Royal College of Arts in London
من الكلية الملكية للفنون في لندن
that have been working together with their tutor, Tony Dunne,
على العمل عليه مع مدرسهم "توني دان"
and with a bunch of scientists around Great Britain
مع مجموعة من العلماء حول بريطانيا
on the possibilities of nanotechnology for design in the future.
على إمكانيات تكنولوجيا النانو للتصميم في المستقبل
New sensing elements on the body --
محسوسات جديدة عل الجسم
you can grow hairs on your nails,
فيمكنك تنمية شعر على أظافرك
and therefore grab some of the particles from another person.
وبالتالي الحصول على بعض الجزيئات من شخص آخر
They seem very, very obsessed
ويبدوا أنهم مهووسون جدا
with finding out more about the ideal mate.
عن فكرة معرفة المزيد عن الشريك المثالي
So they're working on enhancing everything: touch, smell --
لذلك فهم يعملون على تعزيز كل شئ، الملمس، الرائحة
everything they can, in order to find the perfect mate.
أي شئ يستطيعوه لكي يجدوا الشريك الكامل
Very interesting. This is a typeface designer
هذا مثير للإهتمام. و هذا مصمم خطوط
from Israel who has designed -- he calls them "typosperma."
من اسرائيل الذي صمم ما أسماه "تايبو سبيرما" -نطفة ذات خطوط-
He's thinking -- of course it's all a concept --
فهو يفكر - طبعا هذه مازالت أفكار-
of injecting typefaces into spermatozoa,
في حقن خطوط داخل النطفة وداخل "سبيرماتوزا" --
I don't know how to say it in English -- spermatazoi --
لا أعرف كيف أقولها بالإنجليزية -- سبيرماتوزي
in order to make them become -- to almost have a song
لكي يجعلها تحتوي على أغنية
or a whole poem written with every ejaculation. (Laughter)
أو قصيدة كاملة مكتوبة مع كل قذفه (صوت ضحك)
I tell you, designers are quite fantastic, you know.
لقد قلت لكم، المصممين رائعون
So, tissue design.
والآن تصميم الأنسجة
In this case too, you have a mixture of scientists and designers.
في هذه الحالة أيضا مزيج من العلماء و المصممين
This here is part of the same lab at the Royal College of Arts.
هذه هنا من نفس المعمل في الكلية الملكية للفنون
The RCA is really quite an amazing school from that viewpoint.
هذه المدرسة فعلا رائعة في هذا الموضوع
One of the assignments for a year was to work with in-vitro meat.
واحدة من المهام في هذه السنة هو العمل في اللحوم المختبرية
You know that already you can grow meat in vitro.
تعلمون أنه يمكن تربية لحوم في المختبر
In Australia they did it -- this research company, called SymbioticA.
في أستراليا قد قاموا بالفعل في شركة للأبحاث اسمها "سمبيوتكا"
But the problem is that it's a really ugly patty.
لكن المشكلة هي أن شكلها قبيح فعلا
And so, the assignment to the students was,
ولذلك كانت المهمة للطلاب
how should the steak of tomorrow be?
كيف يجب أن تكون شريحة اللحم في المستقبل؟
When you don't have to kill cows and it can have any shape,
عندما لا يكون عليك أن تقتل البقر وباستطاعتك أن تكون أي شكل
what should it be like?
كيف يجب أن يكون شكلها
So this particular student, James King,
لذلك هذا الطالب تحديدا " جيمز كينج"
went around the beautiful English countryside,
ذهب حول الريف الإنجليزي الرائع
picked the best, best cow that he could see,
اختار أفضل بقرة استطاع أن يجدها
and then put her in the MRI machine.
و وضعها في جهاز تصوير الرنين المغناطيسي
Then, he took the scans of the best organs and made the meat --
وأخذ صور أفضل أشكال الأعضاء و صنع اللحم
of course, this is done with a Japanese resins food maker,
بالتأكيد تم عمل هذه بواسطة صانع مواد صمغية ياباني
but you know, in the future it could be made better --
لكن بالتأكيد في المستقبل يمكن تنفيذها بشكل أفضل
which reproduces the best MRI scan of the best cow he could find.
وهذا استنساخ لأفضل صورة رنين مغناطيسي لأفضل بقرة استطاع الحصول عليها
Instead, this element here is much more banal.
ولكن هذا الشكل هنا هو أكثر اعتيادية
Something that you know can be done already
شئ يمكن أن يصنع بالفعل
is to grow bone tissue, so that you can make a wedding ring
هو أن تصنع أنسجة عظام لكي يمكنك صناعة خاتم للزواج
out of the bone tissue of your loved one -- literally.
من أنسجة عظام الشخص الذي تحبه نفسه
So, this is indeed made of human bone tissue.
لذلك فهذه تم عملها من أنسجة عظام إنسان حقيقية
This is SymbioticA, and they've been working --
هذه "سمبيوتكا" كما تعلمون بأنهم كانو يعملون
they were the first ones to do this in-vitro meat --
فهم أول من صنعوا اللحم في المعمل
and now they've also done an in-vitro coat, a leather coat.
و الآن هم يصنعون معطف داخل المعمل، معطف من الجلد
It's miniscule, but it's a real coat. It's shaped like one.
إنه صغير لكنه معطف حقيقي. تم تشكيلها كمعطف
So, we'll be able to really not have any excuse
لذلك فلن يكون لك أي عذر
to be wearing everything leather in the future.
لعدم لبس كل ملابسك من الجلد في المستقبل
One of the most important topics of the show -- you know,
واحده من أهم المواضيع في العرض، كما تعلمون
as anything in our life today,
كأي شئ في حياتنا اليوم
we can look at it from many, many different viewpoints,
نستطيع أن نراها من عدة وجهات نظر مختلفة
and at different levels.
وعدة مستويات
One of the most interesting and most important concepts
واحده من أكثر المفاهيم إثارة للإهتمام و الأهمية
is the idea of scale. We change scale very often:
هي فكرة المقياس، فنحن نغير المقاييس في كثير من الأحيان
we change resolution of screens, and
نحن نغير مقاييس وضوح الشاشة بغير أن نكون
we're not really fazed by it, we do it very comfortably.
منزعجين من ذلك، نفعل ذلك بشكل مريح
So you go, even in the exhibition,
وهكذا، وحتى في المعرض
from the idea of nanotechnology and the nanoscale
من فكرة تكنولوجيا النانو و مقاييس النانو
to the manipulation of really great amounts of data --
وبدلا من معالجة كمية كبيرة من المعلومات
the mapping and tagging of the universe and of the world.
رسم الخرائط ووضع العلامات على الكون و العالم
In this particular case a section will be devoted
و هذه الحالة بالذات تم تكريس قسم خاص
to information design.
لتصميم المعلومات
You see here the work of Ben Fry. This is "Human vs. Chimps" --
و ترون هنا من أعمال "بن فراي". هذه إنسان مقابل شمبانزي
the few chromosomes that distinguish us from chimps.
قليل من الكروموزومات تميزنا عن الشمبانزي
It was a beautiful visualization that he did for Seed magazine.
كانت تخيل مصور رائع تم تنفيذه من أجل مجلة "سييد"
And here's the whole code of Pac-Man, visualized
و هنا رمز كامل مصور ل"باك-مان"
with all the go-to, go-back-to,
مع جميع "إذهب إلى" ، "عد - إلى"
also made into a beautiful choreography.
أيضا صنع استعراض رائع
And then also graphs by scientists,
أيضا
this beautiful diagraph of protein homology.
إنه رسم جميل لحواف لتناظر البروتين
Scientists are starting to also consider aesthetics.
فالعلماء بدأوا يعتقدون في الجماليات
We were discussing with Keith Shrubb* this morning
كنا نناقش ذلك في الصباح مع "كيث شرب"
the fact that many scientists
الحقيقة أن الكثير من العلماء
tend not to use anything beautiful in their presentations,
يميلون إلى عدم إستخدام أي شئ جمالي في عروضهم
otherwise they're afraid of being considered dumb blondes.
فهم يخافون أن يعتبرهم الناس كشقراء غبية
So they pick the worst background
لذلك يختارون أسوأ خلفية
from any kind of PowerPoint presentation, the worst typeface.
من أي نوع من عروض "باور بوينت"، أسوأ الخطوط
It's only recently that this kind of marriage
وفقط حديثا مع هذا الدمج
between design and science is producing some of the first "pretty" --
بين التصميم و العلم ينتج بدايات العرض الجميلة
if we can say so -- scientific presentations.
إذا صح التعبير
Another aspect of contemporary design
جانب آخر للتصميم المعاصر
that I think is mind-opening, promising
أعتقد أنه يوسع الفكر، واعد
and will really be the future of design,
وسيصبح مستقبل التصميم
is the idea of collective design.
وهي فكرة تصميم جماعي
You know, the whole XO laptop, from One Laptop per Child,
كما تعلمون فكرة الكمبيوتر المحمول "OX" و جهاز لكل طفل
is based on the idea of collaboration and mash and networking.
قائمه على فكرة التعاون و التواصل
So, the more the merrier.
لذلك كلما زاد المرح
The more computers, the stronger the signal,
زادت الكمبيوترات، وزادت قوت الإشارة
and children work on the interface so that it's all based
و زاد استخدام الأطفال للأجهزه، لذلك كل الفكرة مبنيه
on doing things together, tasks together.
على العمل معا في نفس المهمام
So the idea of collective design
لذلك ففكرة التصميم المشترك
is something that will become even bigger in the future,
سيزداد حجمه في المستقبل
and this is chosen as an example.
و هذه أختيرت كمثال
Related to the idea of collective design and to the new balance
مرتبطة بفكرة التصميم الجماعي و التوازن
between the individual and the collectiveness, collectivity
بين الأنشطة الفردية و المشتركة
is the idea of existence maximum.
هي فكرة الحد الأقصى للوجود
That's a term that I coined a few years ago
هذا المصطلح الذي اخترعته قبل بضع سنوات
while I was thinking of how pressed we are together,
بينما كنت أفكر كيف كنا مجتمعين
and at the same time how these small objects,
في نفس الوقت هذه الأشياء الصغيرة
like the Walkman first and then the iPod,
مثل "واكمان" في البدايه ثم "الآي-بود" -مشغل الموسيقى-
create bubbles of space around us that enable us
شكلت فقاقيع حولنا جعلتنا نحصل على
to have a metaphysical space
فراغات تخيليه
that is much bigger than our physical space.
أكبر بكثير من الفراغ الحقيقي الذي نشغله
You can be in the subway and you can be completely isolated
فبإمكانك أن تكون في قطار الأنفاق وتصبح معزولا تمام
and have your own room in your iPod.
و تكون في فراغك الخاص في "الآي-بود"
And this is the work of several designers
وهذا من أعمال عدة مصممين
that really enhance the idea of solitude and expansion
التي تدعم فكرة العزلة و التوسع
by means of various techniques.
من خلال تقنيات مختلفة
This is a spa telephone. The idea is that it's become so difficult
هذا هاتف للمنتجعات، فقد أصبح من الصعب
to have a private conversation anywhere
أن تقوم بمحادثة خاصة في أي مكان
that you go to the spa, you have a massage, you have a facial,
كأن تكون في النادي و في جلسة التدليك
maybe a rub, and then you have this beautiful pool
و في حوض السباحة الرائع
with this perfect temperature, and you can have
في درجة حرارة مثالية و بإمكانك الحصول
this isolation tank phone conversation
على محادثة تلفونية في خصوصية
with whomever you've been wanting to talk with for a long time.
مع أي أحد تريد أن تتحدث مع و لوقت طويل
And same thing here, Social Tele-presence.
ونفس الشئ هنا، التواجد عن بعد
It's actually already used by the military a little bit,
يتم استخدامها بالفعل في العسكرية
but it's the idea of being able to be somewhere else
لكنها فكرة إمكانية التواجد في مكان آخر
with your senses while you're removed from it physically.
بحواسك بينما أنت بعيد بالجسد
And this is called Blind Date. It's a [unclear],
وإسمها موعد بدون معرفة مسبقة
so if you're too shy to be really at the date,
لذلك إن كنت تخجل من المواجهات
you can stay at a distance with your flowers
يمكنك الوقوف بعيدا و معك الورد
and somebody else reenacts the date for you.
وشخص آخر سيمثل الموعد بدلا عنك
Rapid manufacturing is another big area
التصنيع السريع مجال كبير آخر
in which technology and design are, I think,
التي أعتقد أعتقد أن التكنولوجيا و التصميم
bound to change the world. You've heard about it before many times.
سيحدثان طفرة في تغيير العالم. سمعتم عنها من قبل عدة مرات
Rapid manufacturing is a computer file
هذه الصناعة ملف كمبيوتر
sent directly from the computer to the manufacturing machine.
يرسل مباشرة من الكمبيوتر الى جهاز التنفيذ
It used to be called rapid prototyping, rapid modeling.
كانت تسمى صناعة النماذج الأولية السريعة
It started out in the '80s, but at the beginning
بدأت في الثمانينات، لكن في البداية
it was machines carving out of a foam block
كانت جهاز ينحت في كتلة من الفوم
a model that was very, very fragile,
نموذج كان هش و ضعيف جدا
and could not have any real use.
و غير صالح لأي استخدام
Slowly but surely, the materials became better -- better resins.
ببطئ ولكن بالتأكيد الخامة أصبحت أفضل -- مادة راتنجية
Techniques became better -- not only carving
التقنية أصبحت أفضل ليس فقط النحت
but also stereolithography and laser -- solidifying all kinds of resins,
لكن أيضا المجسمات و الليزر ترسخ كل أنواع الراتنجات "ريزن"
whether in powder or in liquid form. And the vats became bigger,
سواء كانت مسحوق أو سائل. و المساحة أصبحت أكبر
to the point that now we can have actual chairs
لدرجة أنه بإمكاننا أن ننحت كرسي حقيقي
made by rapid manufacturing.
صنع بواسطة التصنيع السريع
It takes seven days today to manufacture a chair,
اليوم يستغرق 7 أيام لصناعة كرسي
but you know what? One day it will take seven hours.
لكن هل تعرفون؟ يوم ما سيكفي 7 ساعات
And then the dream is that you'll be able to, from home,
حينها الحلم بأن تستطيع من المنزل
customize your chair. You know, companies and designers
عمل كرسيك الخاص. الشركات و المصممين
will be designing the matrix or the margins
سيصممون القوالب و النماذج
that respect both solidity and brand, and design identity.
التي تحترم السلامة و الحقوق والهوية الفكرية
And then you can send it to the Kinko's store at the corner
وبعدها يمكنك إرساله الى متجر"كنكو" القريب
and go get your chair. Now, the implications of this are enormous,
وأحصل على الكرسي. آثار هذه التكنولوجيا ستكون هائلة
not only regarding the participation of the final buyer
ليس فقط مشاركة المشتري النهائي
in the design process, but also no tracking,
في مراحل التصميم
no warehousing, no wasted materials.
لن نحتاج مخازن و لا إلى إضاعة الموارد
Also, I can imagine many design manufacturers
وأيضا أتخيل أن العديد من المصنعيين و المصممين
will have to retool their own business plans
سيتوجب عليهم إعادة النظر في تخطيط إدارة أعمالهم
and maybe invest in this Kinko's store. But it really is a big change.
أو ربما الإستثمار في متاجر "كينكو"
And here I'm showing a picture that was in Wired Magazine --
وهنا أعرض لكم صورة كانت في مجلة "WIRED"
you know, the Artifacts of the Future section that I love so much --
القطع الفنية في المستقبل والتي أحبها كثيرا
that shows you can have your desktop 3D printer
فهي تتنبأ بأنك تستطيع أن يكون لك طابعة ثلاثية الأبعاد
and print your own basketball.
و سيصح بإمكانك طباعة كرة السلة الخاصة بك
But here instead are examples, you can already 3D-print textiles,
ولكن هنا لدينا مثل، فأنت تستطيع بالفعل طباعة ثلاثية الأبعاد على الأقمشة
which is very interesting.
إنها مثيرة للإهتمام فعلا
This is just a really nice touch -- it's called slow prototyping.
و هذه لمسة رائعة فعلا -- إسمها "صناعة النماذج البطيئه"
It's a designer that put 10,000 bees at work and they built this vase.
إنهم مصممون من وضع 10000 نحلة و صنع هذه الفازة الزجاجية
They had a particular shape that they had to stay in.
وكان لديهم شكلا محددا يجب أن يحافظوا عليه.
Mapping and tagging.
رسم الخرائط ووضع العلامات
As the capacity of computers becomes really, really big,
كما أن سعة الكمبيوترات أصبحت كبيرة جدا جدا
and the capacity of our mind not that much bigger,
و سعة عقولنا ليست بهذا الحجم
we find that we need to tag as much as we can what we do
وجدنا أننا نحتاج أن نضع علامات بقدر ما نستطيع
in order to then retrace our path.
لكي نستطيع أن نسترجع دروبنا
Also, we do it in order to share with other people.
أيضا نفعل ذلك كي نتشارك مع الآخرين
Again, this communal sense of experience
مرة أخرى هذه خبرة منطق عام
that seems to be so important today.
الذي يبدو أنه في غاية الأهمية اليوم
So, various ways to map and tag
لذلك عدة طرق للخرائط و وضع علامات
are also the work of many designers nowadays.
وأيضا عمل العديد من المصممين في الوقت الحاضر
Also, the senses -- designers and scientists all work on trying to expand
الحواس، مصممون وعلماء يعملون على محاولة زيادة
our senses capabilities so that we can achieve more.
قدرات حواسنا لنستطيع تحقيق المزيد
And also animal senses in a way.
وحواس الحيوانات أيضا
This particular object that many people love so much
هذا العمل و الذي سيحبه الناس كثيرا
is actually based on kind of a scientific experiment --
هي في الحقيقة مبنية على تجربة علمية
the fact that bees have a very strong olfactory sense,
الحقيقة هي أن النحل لديه حاسة شم قوية
and so -- much like dogs that can smell certain kinds of skin cancer --
ولذلك -- مثل الكلاب التي تستطيع أن تشم أنواع محددة من سرطان الجلد
bees can be trained by Pavlovian reflex
أيضا تم تدريبها بواسطة "بافلوفيان ريفلكس"
to detect one type of cancer, and also pregnancy.
أن تكشف نوع واحد من السرطان و أيضا الحمل.
And so this student at the RCA
وأيضا هؤلاء الطلاب من "RCA"
designed this beautiful blown-glass object
صمموا هذه الزجاجة المنفوخة الجميلة
where the bees move from one chamber to the other
حيث ينتقل النحل من غرفة إلى أخرى
if they detect that particular smell
إذا حددوا رائحة محدده
that signifies, in this case, pregnancy.
و في هذه الحالة هذا يدل على الحمل
Another shape is made for cancer.
و شكل آخر صمم لكشف السرطان
Design for Debate is a very interesting new endeavor
تصميم من أجل النقاش هو محاولة مثيرة للإهتمام
that designers have really shaped for themselves.
أن المصممين قد شكلوا لأنفسهم
Some designers don't design objects, products,
بعض المصممين لا يصممون منتجات و أشكال حسية
things that we're going to actually use,
أو أشياء سنقوم باستخدامها فعلا
but rather, they design scenarios that are object-based.
بل يصممون سيناريوهات للتنفيذ
They're still very useful.
و ما زالوا مفيدين جدا
They help companies and other designers think better about the future.
فهم يساعدون الشركات و المصممين الآخرين أن يفكروا بطريقة أفضل عن المستقبل
And usually they are accompanied by videos.
و غالبا تكون مرفقه بالفيديو
This is quite beautiful. It's Dunne and Raby, "All the Robots."
هذه رائعة فعلا. إنها دون و رابي. كل الربوتات
Those are a series of robots that are meant to be taken care of.
هذه سلسة من الروبوت التي تحتاج أن تهتم بها
We always think that robots will take care of us,
دائما كنا نعتقد أن الروبوت سيعتني بنا
and instead they designed these robots that are very, very needy.
بدلا من ذلك صممت هذه الروبوتات في إحتياج لنا
You need to take one in your arms and look at it in the eyes
ستحتاج أن تأخذ إحداها بين ذراعيك وتنظر الى عينيها
for about five minutes before it does something.
لخمس دقائق قبل أن تفعل شيئا
Another one gets really, really nervous if you get in to the room,
واحدة أخرى ستصبح قلقة إذا دخلت الغرفة
and starts shaking, so you have to calm it down.
وتبدأ في الإهتزاز لذلك تحتاج إلى تهدئتا
So it's really a way to make us think more
فهذه طريقة تدعونا للتفكير
about what robots mean to us.
ماذا تعني الروبوت لنا
Noam Toran and "Accessories for Lonely Men":
ناوم توران و إكسسوارات للرجل الوحيد
the idea is that when you lose your loved one
الفكرة هي عندما تفقد أحدا تحبه
or you go through a bad breakup,
أو تمر بفشل تجربة عاطفية
what you miss the most are those annoying things
أكثر ما تفتقده هي تلك الأشياء المزعجة
that you used to hate when you were with the other person.
ما كنت تكرهه عندما كنت مع الشخص الأخر
So he designed all these series of accessories.
لذلك صممت هذه الإكسسوارات
This one is something that takes away the sheets from you at night.
إحداها شئ يبعد عنك غطاء الفراش أثاء النوم
Then there's another one that breathes on your neck.
بعدها شئ آخر يتنفس عند رقبتك
There's another one that throws plates and breaks them.
وهناك واحد آخر يرمي الأطباق و يكسرها
So it's just this idea of what we really miss in life.
فهي فقط فكرة عن الأشياء التي نفتقدها في الحياه
Elio Caccavale: he took the idea
إليو كوكافالي -- أخذ الفكرة
of those dolls that explain leukemia.
من هذه الدمية التي تشرح سرطان الدم
He's working on dolls that explain xenotransplantation,
انه يعمل على الدمى التي تفسر زراعة الأعضاء
and also the spider gene into the goat, from a few years ago.
من عدة سنوات أيضا نقل جينات من عنكبوت إلى ماعز
He's working for the exhibition on a whole series of dolls
إنه يعمل على معرض عن سلسلة من الدمي "العرائس"
that explain to children where babies come from today.
والتي تشرح للصغار من أين يأتي الأطفال اليوم
Because it's not anymore Mom, Dad, the flowers and the bees,
لأنه ليست فقط أم وأب أو زهور و نحل
and then there's the baby. No, it can be two moms, three dads,
والآن هناك أطفال من عدة أمهات و آباء
in-vitro -- there's the whole idea
في المعمل هناك فكرة كاملة
of how babies can be made today that has changed.
عن كيف يمكن ولادة طفل
So it's a series of dolls that he's working on right now.
إنها مجموعة من العرائس التي يعمل عليها الآن
One of the most beautiful things
واحدة من أجمل الأشياء
is that designers really work on life,
هي أن المصممين لا يعملون فقط على الحياة
even though they take technology into account.
حتى وأنهم يضعون التكنولوجيا الجديدة في الحسبان
And many designers have been working recently
والعديد من المصممين قد بدؤوا العمل
on the idea of death and mourning,
على فكرة الموت و الحداد
and what we can do about it today with new technologies.
وماذا نستطيع أن نفعل حيالها بوجود التكتولوجيا الحديثة
Or how we should behave about it with new technologies.
أو كيف يكون تصرفنا معها في وجود هذه التكنولوجيات
These three objects over there are hard drives
هذه العناصر الثلاث هناك عبارة عن 3 أقراص صلبه
with a Bluetooth connection. But they're in reality
مع بلوتوث لنقل المعلومات اللاسلكية. لكنها في الحقيقة
very, very beautiful sculpted artifacts
منحوتات فنيه رائعة
that contain the whole desktop and computer memory
والتي تحتوي على ذاكرة كمبيوتر كامل
of somebody who passed away.
خاصة بشخص توفى
So instead of having only the pictures,
فبدلا من وجود صور فقط
you will be able to put this object next to the computer
يمكنك وضع هذه العناصر بجوار الكمبيوتر
and all of a sudden have, you know,
وبدون أي مقدمات، سيكون لديك
Gertrude's whole life and all of her files
كل حياة جيرترود وملفاتها
and her address book come alive.
و دفتر عناوينها ظهر مرة أخرى
And this is even better. This is Auger-Loizeau, "AfterLife."
هذه أفضل. هذه "أوجر - لويزياو" ما بعد الحياة
It's the idea that some people don't believe in an afterlife.
الفكرة في أن بعض الناس لا يعتقدون في الحياة الأخرى
So to give them something tangible that shows that
و لإعطائهم شيئا ملموسا يمكن أن يريهم أنه
there is something after death, they take the gastric juices
يوجد شئ بعد الممات. يمكنهم أخذ عصارات المعدة
of people who passed away and concentrate them,
لأشخاص ماتو و تركيزها
and put them into a battery that can actually be used
و وضعها في بطاريات يمكن إستخدامها
to power flashlights. They also go -- you know, sex toys, whatever.
للإضاءة وربما أيضا يمكن للعبة جنسية أو أي شئ آخر
It's quite amazing how these things can make you smile,
إنها رائعة كيف يمكن لهذه الأشياء تجعلك تبتسم
can make you laugh, can make you cry sometimes.
أو تضحك أو ربما تبكي في أوقات أخرى
But I'm hoping that this particular exhibition
لكن أنا آمل أن يستطيع هذا المعرض
will be able to trace a new portrait of where design is going --
أن يتتبع إلى أين يذهب التصميم الجديد
which is always, hopefully, a portrait a few years in advance
الذي هو دائما كما نأمل هو صورة لعدة أعوام قادمة
of where the world is going.
لأين يذهب العالم
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا